<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://thecurryspice.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://thecurryspice.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-08-07T22:28:52+00:00</updated><id>https://thecurryspice.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Akhil R. Baranwal</title><subtitle>Welcome to my website. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">2025 already, is it?</title><link href="https://thecurryspice.github.io/blog/2025/2025-already/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="2025 already, is it?"/><published>2025-01-23T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://thecurryspice.github.io/blog/2025/2025-already</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thecurryspice.github.io/blog/2025/2025-already/"><![CDATA[<p>3 weeks of this year are done.<br/> 6% of the year has passed.<br/> 1 part out of 20 is done.<br/> ooof.<br/> Time goes fast especially when you want it to go slow.<br/> So do vacations.</p> <hr/> <p><br/></p> <h2 id="sunsets">Sunsets</h2> <p>Like a heavily loaded train that tries to accelerate from zero to its top speed, I pull my carriages with effort. I had almost forgotten how excruciating it is to regain top speed after it reaches zero. Zero. The peak of inertia. The trench of output. But was it even a vacation if momentum didn’t reduce to zero? But are vacations supposed to do that? If the train dreads the zero after the stop, does it have to do with the train or the stop? This is an endless debate, like one between a Contrarian and an Opportunist.</p> <p>I don’t have a liking towards routine. But I still very much like watching sunsets. SFU offers breathtaking sunsets. This one was captured at <a href="https://maps.app.goo.gl/KvUEokazi6Zd9FET7">this spot</a>.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/posts/blog/2025-01-23/SFUSunsetSouthWest-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/posts/blog/2025-01-23/SFUSunsetSouthWest-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/posts/blog/2025-01-23/SFUSunsetSouthWest-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/posts/blog/2025-01-23/SFUSunsetSouthWest.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="SFU Offers breathtaking sunsets" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> Isn't this breathtaking? I don't know about you, my breath gets taken away every time. </div> <p>December felt like a sunset. Majestic and grand, irrespective of how cloudy the entire year was. I don’t even remember the details of the day, just the memory of a peaceful sun setting on the horizon of honest work done.</p> <hr/> <p><br/></p> <h2 id="sunrises">Sunrises</h2> <p>January is the Monday after a super long weekend. Half of January is spent in catching up on becoming relevant again. Messages. Emails. And that one guy who’d still wishes greetings for the New Year on the 15th. God bless his enthusiasm. (Where does he get it from? asking for a friend…)<br/> For a brown guy not getting the sun a lot, seasonal depression is quite real. Why couldn’t the year start somewhere around the vernal equinox? Spring’s bloom in bright sunlight might inspire me to come out of my house, however dazed.</p> <p>Momentum lost on Monday impacts the entire week. Each day you spend catching on the previous day. The entire week is spent catching up on itself. Or so I thought… So much of our time is spent in measuring progress relative to the destination, which appears as far away as when we started our journey. Sometimes, it’s not time that we chase, but vindication. We want to be reasonable, we want to justify our intent, and above all, rationalise our choices.<br/> The irony is that we seek this vindication from ourselves. Again, a debate between an Opportunist who justifies and a Contrarian who denies. And endless debate.</p> <p>I let them debate. I watch the sunrise instead. I focus on the gorgeous shades that the dawn colours the sky in, and how the sunlight animates the leaves on the silhouettes of trees. The contrarian and the opportunist stop their debate. All this time, I learnt to appreciate the sunrise, so that they may be inspired to see the next one. It was only when I learnt to see the mountains that I realised that the mountains that are purple against the rising sun can also sport an amber glow when the sun sets on the opposite horizon.<br/> It was never about the sunrise or the sunset.<br/> It was always about what I found worth looking at.</p> <hr/>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="blogpost"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[3 weeks of this year are done. 6% of the year has passed. 1 part out of 20 is done. ooof. Time goes fast especially when you want it to go slow. So do vacations.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Restarting in 2024</title><link href="https://thecurryspice.github.io/blog/2024/micron-imagination-hiaccel/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Restarting in 2024"/><published>2024-10-12T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-10-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://thecurryspice.github.io/blog/2024/micron-imagination-hiaccel</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thecurryspice.github.io/blog/2024/micron-imagination-hiaccel/"><![CDATA[<p>Hmm… The world ended in March 2020. We are all ghosts today. Or, well, were at least supposed to be, instead of the loves ones that became ghosts.</p> <p>Four years later, so much has changed.<br/> Take <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Jekyll</code>, for example. I make this post after 3 hours of peeling my eyes and pulling my hair while scrolling through StackOverflow. It took me about forty trials to set up <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">rbenv</code> and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Jekyll</code> correctly, just to add this post.<br/> Frankly, I don’t even know if the current setup is how it should be installed. All I know is that it works.<br/> Every new configuration line I add feels like removing a block from a Jenga tower. No matter how carefully I deal with this setup, it is bound to collapse in the future. As for the past, I would be remiss to not admit I haven’t been active here since about the past three years. Here’s a quick recap.</p> <hr/> <p><br/></p> <h2 id="micron">Micron</h2> <p>By the end of two years at Micron, I owned the verification for the host-interface to our <strong>first UFS 4.0 controller</strong>. I wrote firmware, debugged waveforms, debugged datapath software on FPGA emulations, debugged link errors during post-silicon validation, and eventually got to a stage where I had enough understanding about the architecture to write high-performance firmware.<br/> What I cherished most though, was talking to engineers from multiple geographies and finding that everyone is as confused as the other. But engineers have this flex, that they hammer something here and wrench something there and find precisely and exactly what is wrong. The redemption of information and knowledge in that moment is nothing short of an adrenaline rush.</p> <p>There are 3 key moments during my verification experience that I will never forget.</p> <ol> <li>The most bugs I have found as a verification engineer were obviously in my own code. I remember facing a complex issue related to a datapath hang (which can occur due to any of its constituent IPs failing) that was found out to be a RTL issue. Pointers are quite common in high performance firmware (and they do nothing more than organise memory addressing). However, one flaw in a multi-level organisation of memory addresses can have effects that can easily push a developer to insanity. What I finally realised, after about two days of debugging (and I quote from my journal) was: <blockquote> <p>“There’s a pointer (P) to a pointer to a structure of pointers to lists of pointers to decoder-buffers (D). Pointer P receives an invalid value due to wrong arithmetic and makes the datapath hang because the decoder tries to access something not available on its memory bus. Ooof!”</p> </blockquote> </li> <li> <p>The second moment was <a href="/folio/news/announcement_5">validating the signs of silicon life in the first tapeout of my career</a></p> </li> <li>Working with post-silicon validation was humbling, to say the least. The bursts that would take 30 hours to simulate on compute-farms would take 20 ms to finish in the real world. During the later days of post-silicon validation with an actual host, we were seeing an error in one of our end-to-end tests, where the device would be able transfer TiBs of data in low-performance modes, but would fail towards the trailing end of 2MiB when using its full bandwidth. This was weird. We rinsed through the firmware looking for modules going out of coordination after transferring ~2MiB of data. Next, we re-simulated everything in RTL. Several discussions ensued. There was a brooding sense of fear that maybe verification of some RTL misbehaviour was omitted.<br/> Whenever this happens, it is a great time to understand who likes to point fingers and who likes to own their code.<br/> A week later, different sort of expensive gadgets and scopes were brought in to log these real world transfers at 40Gbps happening on a 1W power budget. I kid you not, we checked <em>everything</em> from the firmware binary and handshake signals to the voltage measurements on the copper wires. Everything couldn’t have been better. So, <strong>what was wrong</strong>? The team who was responsible for the hardware testbed boards offered to redo the entire setup. Their request was dismissed twice, under the claim that doing so would increase the work and introduce unknown errors instead of solving the obvious ones right now. The third time, they were allowed to do it. I was there with one of the other engineers when the frontend host interface was being disassembled. What we found while intending to clean the 8 coaxial copper cables that connected the RX-TX lanes between the host and the device, left us looking at each other almost on the simultaneous verge of tears and laughter. For some reason, I remember that moment with the memory of the tone that used to play when Mario would lose a life.<br/> These elite gold-plated coaxial cables had a pin at the centre, and a small tubular shielding on the side. A small section, hardly 20 degrees out of 360, of one of these cables had chipped off and was hanging loose. The touch of a finger dropped this gold plated flake on the white desk. It was this flake that was the reason that low-speed transfers worked flawlessly, but high-speed (high frequency) transfers saw all sorts of weird capacitance effects making the transfer fail roughly around the time when 2MiBs had been transferred. <strong>1/12th of a 3mm tubular connector failing, overruled all the fault tolerance we had designed in all five layers of the communication stack ദ്ദി ༎ຶ‿༎ຶ )</strong> - from the link level to the application firmware.</li> </ol> <p>There’s an unpopular saying in the semiconductor industry, I understood it in that moment.</p> <blockquote> <p>“Semiconductor Engineering industry is not rocket science. It’s more complex”</p> </blockquote> <hr/> <p><br/></p> <h2 id="imagination">Imagination</h2> <p>Saying goodbye to Micron was a tough decision. I was <em>restarting</em> my career as a design engineer, essentially discarding the headstart and promotions I would have enjoyed had I stayed in verification. Imagination Technologies had already worked on an in-order CPU core, that they were trying to expand into a ASIL-D certified processor. The weight of responsibility is crazy. You certainly don’t want the processor to delay triggering the Collision Avoidance System (CAS) because it was busy blinking the lights for the lane-assist.</p> <p>Linting and CDC is mostly what was on my plate initially, and I was offered to work on a reset synchronisation logic for the lock-step cores. High frequency designs are structured very differently than high bandwidth designs. There was a lot to learn, and I started feeling that there was a lot more that I wanted to explore. I decided to pack my bags for future studies in designing hardware accelerators.</p> <hr/> <p><br/></p> <h2 id="vancouver">Vancouver</h2> <p>I moved to Vancouver in Fall 2023. Some folks like the mountains. Some like the beach. Vancouver offers both!</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/posts/blog/2024-10-12/IonaTerminus-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/posts/blog/2024-10-12/IonaTerminus-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/posts/blog/2024-10-12/IonaTerminus-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/posts/blog/2024-10-12/IonaTerminus.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="Somewhere around Iona Terminus" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> Somewhere around Iona Terminus </div> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/posts/blog/2024-10-12/WhiteRock-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/posts/blog/2024-10-12/WhiteRock-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/posts/blog/2024-10-12/WhiteRock-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/posts/blog/2024-10-12/WhiteRock.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="Somewhere around White Rock" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> Somewhere around White Rock </div> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/posts/blog/2024-10-12/StanleyPark-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/posts/blog/2024-10-12/StanleyPark-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/posts/blog/2024-10-12/StanleyPark-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/posts/blog/2024-10-12/StanleyPark.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="Somewhere around Stanley Park" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> Somewhere around Stanley Park </div> <hr/> <p><br/> <br/></p> <h2 id="sfu">SFU</h2> <p>It is very important to choose where to stay while studying, and I feel lucky to have found accommodation at SFU’s on-campus housing. It makes a huge difference. Here are a couple of photos from SFU campus. Both are HDR shots from a Samsung phone. No post edits. Someone professional might capture much better photos.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/posts/blog/2024-10-12/campusFall-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/posts/blog/2024-10-12/campusFall-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/posts/blog/2024-10-12/campusFall-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/posts/blog/2024-10-12/campusFall.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="campusFall" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> Sharad. Autumn. Here, it's called Fall because well ... leaves ... fall down. Captured late-October. </div> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/posts/blog/2024-10-12/campusMountain-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/posts/blog/2024-10-12/campusMountain-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/posts/blog/2024-10-12/campusMountain-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/posts/blog/2024-10-12/campusMountain.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="campusMountain" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> Always better to cry amidst mountains than on a busy street. Yes, this view is from campus. Captured mid-March. </div> <p>The occasional deer and bear sightings are a bonus. The air is cleaning out my lungs as quickly as the expenses are clearing out my wallet. It is fun to return to student life. But let me not romanticise it for you. In another universe, I probably wouldn’t have liked this change in lifestyle. This type of a lifestyle change is quite subjective and is only for the brave at heart.<br/> I am able to survive the delusion that I am ᕕ(⌐■_■)ᕗ ♪♬</p> <p>hehe.</p> <hr/> <p><br/> <br/></p> <h2 id="hiaccel">HiAccel</h2> <p><a href="https://www.sfu.ca/~zhenman/group.html">HiAccel Lab</a> works on a breadth of topics related to computer engineering - HPC accelerators, novel architectures, and compiler support for the same. I am glad to continue my research on accelerator-rich architectures with brilliant, clever colleagues who share my interests and frustrations.</p> <p>Three years ago, I had stopped updating this space.<br/> So what happened now? Did a horse kick my head?<br/> Why am I starting to write this blog again? Nobody reads it anyway.<br/> I don’t know. But maybe humans scream the loudest when nobody is listening. I shall scream into this void here, laying down human thoughts for some web-scraping AI chatbot to adopt into its learning of what makes text human.</p> <p>I often wonder where I will fit better - academia or corporate.<br/> I don’t know, honestly. All I know is that I am trying to find the right place, and just hang around.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/posts/unsorted/calvinhobbesrightplacetime-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/posts/unsorted/calvinhobbesrightplacetime-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/posts/unsorted/calvinhobbesrightplacetime-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/posts/unsorted/calvinhobbesrightplacetime.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="CHRightPlaceTime" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="blogpost"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Hmm… The world ended in March 2020. We are all ghosts today. Or, well, were at least supposed to be, instead of the loves ones that became ghosts.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">On Finding Your Zima Blue</title><link href="https://thecurryspice.github.io/blog/2021/on-finding-your-zima-blue/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On Finding Your Zima Blue"/><published>2021-12-25T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-12-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://thecurryspice.github.io/blog/2021/on-finding-your-zima-blue</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thecurryspice.github.io/blog/2021/on-finding-your-zima-blue/"><![CDATA[<hr/> <p><br/> <br/></p> <p><strong>SPOILER ALERT</strong>: This article contains spoilers for the “Love, Death + Robots” series on Netflix.</p> <p>Last night, my friends and I discussed the concept of <strong>Zima Blue</strong> on an unconventional tangent. Zima Blue is Episode 14 from the <a href="https://www.netflix.com/in/title/80174608">Netflix Series “Love Death + Robots”</a>. If you haven’t watched this series, I humbly request and strongly recommend you to consider watching this one. The episodes are all independent stories unrelated to each other, and each episode is roughly 15 minutes in length.</p> <p>Here’s a fantastic trailer. You might want to reduce the volume by a couple units:</p> <div style="text-align:center"> <iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/wUFwunMKa4E" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div> <p><br/> <br/> Every episode is unique and special; they are all a jarring escapade from routine life. Some or the other way, most episodes gave me <em>atleast</em> something to think about. However, Episode 14 (Zima Blue), left me in absolute turmoil and chaos. I remember tossing around in bed that night, my stomach sinking in multiple times from a mentally exhausting and haunting deliberation of the underlying meaning.</p> <p>Skip this paragraph if you don’t want a revisit of the episode:<br/> The world thinks that Zima, a famous and acclaimed artist, is a human who over time has undergone radical biological procedures which enabled him to tolerate extreme environments without the burden of a protective suit. His eyes could see in any known spectrum, and he no longer breathed oxygen. Zima is in search of his true purpose and has been pushing the boundaries of science and art to find it. Zima’s murals begin featuring a blue square in the middle of the canvas. With every new piece he creates, this blue square takes a larger portion of the paintings, until Zima unveils an entirely blue mural. Zima Blue. Zima explains that his search for truth was outward, into the cosmos and he soon realized that his focus should turn inward, looking for his origins. Zima reveals that he is actually not a human, but a robot, which was built to clean a swimming pool. That was the very first moment that it had enough intelligence to perceive its surroundings and <em>extract some simple pleasure from the execution of a task well done</em>. For his last piece of art, Zima slowly disintegrates himself in a swimming pool, finally becomes a little robot, and starts cleaning it.</p> <h2 id="my-interpretation">My Interpretation</h2> <p>To me, the blue square represents an unconventional means to a conventional end. The painting is a conventional end; the blue square is the unconventional means. The conventional perspective will find the blue square juxtaposed against the painting of the cosmos. It’s as if the blue square is <em>destroying</em> the conventional perspective. But, through a deeply personal and non-conventional perspective, Zima seems to find so much meaning in the presence of this shade of blue that he keeps drawing this square larger and larger.</p> <p>To me, Zima committed suicide for his final piece. This suicide, is slightly nuanced though. It did not end his life, rather, it was the suicide of the external personality that Zima had become in the eyes of the audience. However, that’s not the crux of my sleepless nights; <strong>I’m more interested in chancing upon a Zima Blue moment</strong>.<br/> Think of it this way: What conspired Zima to paint a blue square in the middle of the canvas? Why did he <em>feel</em> the need to do it?<br/> What is more haunting is the fact that Zima had to commit suicide to finally find ‘meaning’, whatever sense he makes out of that word! What does this represent? You have to burn something down to build something back from the base? That you have to fall once to finally rise? That you have to un-make yourself to finally … make yourself?<br/> I’ve consistently thought about how to find my own personal Zima-Blue moments - which are moments where one realises some deeply-personal, non-conventional element to their life. I hoped that after getting Zima-Blued, I too could extract some simple pleasure from the execution of a task well done.</p> <h2 id="getting-zima-blued">Getting Zima-Blued</h2> <p>Zima-Blue moments must come naturally. I have two reasons why getting Zima-Blued cannot be contrived or forced:<br/></p> <ol> <li>I know most of the <strong>conventional(C)/non-conventional(NC)</strong> means to most ends. If I knew that taking a certain means will land me up in a certain end, I would have chosen the best option already. There can only be two sets in which my Zima-Blue moment lies - either <strong>(a)</strong> I’m taking the NC path where the C path had to be taken, or <strong>(b)</strong> vice versa. Our schooling/upbringing programs us to behave in certain C ways. It is only through our experiences that we scrutinise all of these C behaviours and choose whether to keep acting on them or choose an alternative NC path towards a selected end. So we are already taking care of <em>(a)</em>. This means that the only paths we failed to take <em>(b)</em>, are the ones where we were initially programmed to do C, and we chose to perform C even after scrutinising it personally. In other words, we didn’t even consider that we can ever take these NC paths, because we calculated that these simply don’t exist.</li> <li>If I can contrive getting Zima-Blued, I will be able to contend that all my non-conventional actions are in pursuit of finding my Zima-Blue moment. That’s a recipe for unbridled chaos. I can kick a dog and say that I wanted to do this because maybe I’ll find meaning in that. I’m not ready for either the philosphical pain or the moral weight that I will endure while trying to live this way.</li> </ol> <p>When we are programmed with a C path, and through scrutiny we realise that we must perform C only, we create a bias. This is one solid reason why Zima-Blue moments cannot be contrived, because the Zima-Blue is on the NC path, but I’m consistently making a bias towards the C path. Worst thing about biases, we don’t get to know about it unless someone explicitly points it out.<br/> So essentially, what we want to do is to increase the probability of choosing the NC path, given that in reality we would choose the C path.<br/> In short:<br/> <strong>Getting Zima-Blued = P(A|B)</strong><br/> A is “acted or chose NC”<br/> B is “originally intending to choose C”</p> <p>Under normal circumstances, this probability is really low because we have already calculated that the C path brings more returns, or guarantees lesser losses. But when people engage in experiences singificantly out of their usual life, they increase their chances of hitting this probability. For example, many people claim that travelling around the world changed their life. Or when people who are used to desk-jobs are thrown into the oceans with scuba-diving equipment, they feel a strange sense of insignificance and peace. Maybe they just came across a NC path.</p> <h2 id="intoxication">Intoxication</h2> <p>I never thought I’d ever find a conclusive, logical reason to even consider intoxication/drugs as an activity I would endorse.<br/> Since getting Zima-Blued implies acting differently than our biases, it is easy to conclude that while intoxicated, people think and perceive the world in unconventional ways. This means that even though they would always intend the C path, their thoughts and actions will become corrupted, leading to actualisation of the NC path. Choosing this NC path and not acting as per our biases, is a gentle un-making, a mini-suicide of our personal self, something Zima Blue so deeply signified. So, (the responsible use of) drugs could actually provide a neat little method to increase our chances of getting Zima-Blued.<br/> One needs to loosen up <em>just enough</em> to steer away from the conventional routes. However, it is also absolutely important to have a trustworthy friend/guide on the side to help us not steer off a cliff.</p> <blockquote> <p>May your trip be good, for you shall loosen up the mood. Your friendly guide won’t bellow, so Zima-Blue doth flow.<br/> – Ancient Indian proverb</p> </blockquote>]]></content><author><name>Akhil Raj Baranwal</name></author><category term="blogpost"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">On Potential and Capacity</title><link href="https://thecurryspice.github.io/blog/2021/on-potential-and-capacity/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On Potential and Capacity"/><published>2021-06-13T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-06-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://thecurryspice.github.io/blog/2021/on-potential-and-capacity</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thecurryspice.github.io/blog/2021/on-potential-and-capacity/"><![CDATA[<p>Having a routine adjusted to 100% of one’s potential is unpropitious.<br/> Allow me to explain…</p> <p>Computer systems usually have a significant dissociation between user-mode and kernel-mode.<br/> In significantly layman terms, user-mode is an unprivileged state of the CPU, wherein a process is not allowed to do activities that might compromise the health/stability/security of the system. It prevents direct interaction with system peripherals, or memory locations which have not yet been explicitly assigned, etc.<br/> This monumental, managerial task of maintaining each process’ state and monitoring authorisations and accesses, is handled by the kernel. So, in significantly more layman terms, kernel-mode is a privileged state of the CPU, where a process can access everything that is in the capacity of the system.<br/> <em>Since the kernel itself is running on the system, it must take some space within the system’s installed memory</em>. Furthermore, the Operating System itself will take a significant amount of memory and storage within the system’s components. A system installed with 8 GiBs of RAM wouldn’t have all that memory available for launching applications on the operating system. <em>To be really honest, expecting the advertised 8GiBs of performance is irrational</em>.<br/> We can conclude that there’s a difference between the <strong>maximum capacity</strong> of a machine, and a <strong>healthy potential</strong> of a functioning system.</p> <h2 id="examinations-and-benchmarks">Examinations and Benchmarks</h2> <p>I feel there’s a significant difference between conducting an evaluation and conducting a performance benchmark.<br/> Performance benchmarks are handy for analysing machines employed to do a certain task. The fact that many organisations employ humans to do a certain task by analysing their performance benchmarks will come as no surprise. I think that part of the reason this is true is because most evaluative components for humans incline more towards the maximum output that can be generated for a workload within a short span, rather than a wholesome evaluation all inclusive of the same workload but spread across a sufficient time interval.<br/> Most people do not evaluate themselves on the basis of how they perform over an average timeline. Maybe this is because of the numerous times the education system judges us on this absolute metric. It’s like we personally recognise our worth and potential according to the absolute scale, the maximum potential that we can achieve over 3 hours in a closed room. This leads to people judging themselves on not being able to catch up to this high reference potential which is actually a performance benchmark. Doing this is nothing short of self-laceration.</p> <p>Just like the kernel in a system always reserves some memory space for itself from the total memory pool, humans should factor in their time for leisure and wellbeing from their total available time.<br/> Hustling is important, but there must be something worth hustling for.<br/> Decoupling the idea of submitting to one’s purpose from the idea of submitting to one’s work is an important challenge that everyone must try to overcome.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="blogpost"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Having a routine adjusted to 100% of one’s potential is unpropitious. Allow me to explain…]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">For The Earth That Is Dying</title><link href="https://thecurryspice.github.io/blog/2020/for-the-earth-that-is-dying/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="For The Earth That Is Dying"/><published>2020-11-02T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-11-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://thecurryspice.github.io/blog/2020/for-the-earth-that-is-dying</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thecurryspice.github.io/blog/2020/for-the-earth-that-is-dying/"><![CDATA[<p>Our Earth is dying. I don’t need to explain or prove this. All knowledgable folks on this planet already know how we have set it up for doom, unless we act on averting it now. If 7 billion humans can ‘mistakenly’ destroy an entire planet, they can also revive it back into full spring.</p> <p>In all honesty, I have a terribly soft spot for the Earth’s bio-diversity. Be it the evolution of funky birds and their quirky dances to attract a potential prom-date or be it the wrestling of two beetles for territory - a small branch on a shrub. As a kid, I used to watch <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Animal_Planet">Animal Planet</a>, a brilliant television channel that streamed documentaries about animals. Scenes from these documentaries kicked my heart in all directions, mocking how minuscule the scale of my experiences was. I have no shame in admitting that watching such documentaries, coupled with amazing cinematography, pushes me into an intense swirl of emotions, which seldom erupts out as a teardrop.<br/> As a <strong>gift</strong> from my side, here’s a 2-minute video on walruses. Walruses dive in the oceans to hunt for prey and then come up to the icy shore to rest. However, since the ice-sheet is rapidly narrowing and thinning, the walruses have to seek refuge on rocky cliffs. What follows, can not be described in words alone.</p> <div style="text-align:center"> <iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/qVJzQc9ELTE" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe><br/> This is just a couple of minutes of the second episode of the Our Planet series. </div> <p><br/> <br/> To realise that somehow, indirectly, I am part of the reason why walruses in Russia go through this, is incredibly heart-wrenching.<br/> My interest to work on better compute-architectures is not a mere application of my passion for all things electronics and programming. It is significantly fuelled by a deep-rooted interest to avert the climate crisis.</p> <p><strong>Why should I optimise compute clusters though?</strong> Is it that significant?<br/> Compute clusters, data farms, etc, use insane amounts of energy. For example, <a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/robertbryce/2020/10/21/googles-dominance-is-fueled-by-zambia-size-amounts-of-electricity/?sh=25dc54d268c9">this Forbes article</a> describes how Google alone uses about <strong>12.4 terawatt hours</strong> of electricity in 2019. To put this in perspective, this much energy is more than enough to power entire Sri Lanka for a year!<br/> Optimising an architecture by even 1% is a great contribution towards controlling irreversible damage.</p> <p>But you might claim that making better engines for vehicles, moving to renewable sources of energy, etc are better ideas. What I feel is that some physical conditions constrain the efficiencies we can achieve. For example, the concept of Carnot cycle, on which the air-conditioner/refrigerator work, is only about 70% efficient in the present day. If your refrigerator is about 8-10 years old, the efficiency will be about 40-45%.<br/> Because humans have an <em>operating temperature range</em> (outside which they simply die, pfff pathetic), all thermodynamics related to energy-conversion needs to happen around this temperature. Now, this temperature range is not a suitable condition for achieving maximum efficiency. Safe to say, it will be impractical to achieve extremely efficient devices in the near future.<br/></p> <p>We are going to need a lot of compute in the years to come. Everything in the world is shifting to a digital landscape - from research simulations to government documentations. I feel that a shortage of silicon is underway. I think that markets related to semiconductor materials will become an immense factor in economy.<br/> To humanity, as it stands right now, finding a planet with rich reserves of pure silicon is much more valuable than finding a planet of diamonds!<br/> This explosion of semiconductor requirement is in some ways, similar to the trends in the transport industry. Cars and bikes are akin to personal electronic devices; and cargo ships and airlines are compute clusters managed by large corporations. Everyone will be using these technologies at some point. It took several decades before regulations on engine-emissions were enforced. Consequently, new engines were designed, leading to cleaner alternatives.<br/> However this time, we’re significantly aware of our impact on the environment. Emission standards and power regulations already set in place for compute farms or coin-mining facilities are doing a good job. But a better job can be done. Before we actually face a crisis of smoke, we can start building a better engine for the future.</p> <p>That’s why I want to optimise compute, even though we have it fast enough for now.<br/> That’s also why I turn off that extra light that’s still on.<br/> Not because it will, later on, at some point in time, matter in the grand perspective. No.<br/> I turn it off because it matters, right now, in this moment.<br/> I turn it off for me; for the Earth that is dying.</p>]]></content><author><name>Akhil Raj Baranwal</name></author><category term="blogpost"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Our Earth is dying. I don’t need to explain or prove this. All knowledgable folks on this planet already know how we have set it up for doom, unless we act on averting it now. If 7 billion humans can ‘mistakenly’ destroy an entire planet, they can also revive it back into full spring.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Why Are Cyborgs Feasible?</title><link href="https://thecurryspice.github.io/blog/2020/cyborgs/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why Are Cyborgs Feasible?"/><published>2020-07-18T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-07-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://thecurryspice.github.io/blog/2020/cyborgs</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thecurryspice.github.io/blog/2020/cyborgs/"><![CDATA[<p>In a world full of crazy experiments fueled by the desire to understand how we work, can we ever hack our own selves?</p> <hr/> <h2 id="dragonflies">Dragonflies</h2> <p>are amazing creatures, respected for their preying capabilities. As a child, I wondered how dragonflies could catch prey with such agility, while in-flight. Dragonflies have an impressive 97% kill ratio, and most of these kills are done in flight!<br/> I used to wonder how the dragonfly could manage to process such voluminous data in such a small brain size. The answer to this question was found in <a href="https://www.pnas.org/content/110/2/696">this research article</a>, the essence of which is showing that a group of <strong>only 16 neurons</strong> that directly descend towards the wings are able to control the dragonfly’s mid-flight trajectory as the dragonfly notices a prey. This entire article has been shortly summarised in the following video, where researchers attach electrodes to these neurons and show the dragonfly’s behaviour towards prey and predators.</p> <div style="text-align:center"><div style="position:relative;height:0;padding-bottom:56.25%"><iframe src="https://embed.ted.com/talks/lang/en/greg_gage_how_a_dragonfly_s_brain_is_designed_to_kill" width="854" height="480" style="position:absolute;left:0;top:0;width:100%;height:100%" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div></div> <p><br/> Essentially, the gist is simple. Only 16 neurons are able to make the dragonfly move in the direction of the prey. What’s interesting to note is that this behaviour is hardwired; it’s a reflex. The dragonfly <strong>doesn’t think</strong> before moving towards the prey. There’s no thought process involving:<br/> <em>“Ooh, a tasty insect. Let’s eat”</em><br/> <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">&lt;loop&gt;</code><br/> <em>“Oh it’s moving this way”</em><br/> <em>“I should maneuver in such a way that my trajectory crosses the insect’s estimated trajectory”</em><br/> <em>“Ah, I should compensate for this wind”</em><br/> <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">&lt;/loop&gt;</code><br/> <em>“yum yum. Nice”</em>.</p> <p>The thought process simply is:<br/> <em>“Ooh, a tasty insect. Let’s eat”</em><br/> <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">&lt;loop&gt;</code><br/> <em>Cool hardwired stuff.</em><br/> <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">&lt;/loop&gt;</code><br/> <em>“yum yum. Nice”</em>.</p> <hr/> <p><br/> <br/></p> <h2 id="thoughts">Thoughts</h2> <p>are expensive, and it takes a lot of energy to generate the electrical impulses required to think.<br/> So, what causes us to think? In terms of evolution, what reasons us into beginning an act of expending energy which seemingly serves no tangible purpose?<br/></p> <p>For a moment, let’s consider how you think.<br/></p> <ol> <li>You might say that you hear a little voice inside of yourself that talks to you; that you have an <em>internal monologue</em> going on inside yourself.</li> <li>You might say that you’re able to <em>see</em> words or abstract pictures form as you think those words, which means you have <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Internal_monologue#Absence_of_an_internal_monologue">an absence of internal monologue</a>.</li> </ol> <p>An interesting observation is that people in different groups don’t really believe that <em>another</em> way of thinking can exist. This means that even though people have a similar language, they don’t really have the same neural pathways to parse that language!<br/> The point to take away here is that the brain is essentially a black box which goes through enough reinforcement learning in a given number of years to be able to parse data reliably.<br/> <em>Language in itself is like a dynamic programming tool for the human brain.</em><br/></p> <p>For example, take a moment, and think of a jumping elephant. An elephant, maybe huge, maybe small, jumping, it’s tail flailing with that act.<br/> Now, if you really think about this elephant, one of two things may have occured:</p> <ol> <li>You might have imagined the jumping elephant. Kudos to your imagination, because elephants actually can’t jump.</li> <li>You might have simply refuted to think of a jumping elephant because you know for a fact that elephants cannot jump. Kudos to your memory, it significantly controls what you think.</li> </ol> <p>In any case, you hypothesized about the existence of the jumping elephant. You tried reconstructing a fictitious representation from memory and immediately modelled a virtual environment to test your hypothesis. Depending on the rules that your memory put forth, you either imagined the elephant jumping, or you didn’t.<br/> And all of that happened because I uttered a specific series of words of a common <em>language</em>, which you parsed at your level of understanding.<br/> Beautiful, isn’t it?</p> <p>Yuval Noah Harari, in his wonderful book <a href="https://www.amazon.in/Sapiens-Humankind-Yuval-Noah-Harari/dp/0099590085">Sapiens</a>, reasons this habit of humans creating fictional thoughts inside their massive brains. I find myself particularly fascinated by the fact that the Neanderthals (Homo neanderthalensis, the stereotypical “caveman” body type) had almost equivalent (if not more) brain volume as compared to Homo Sapiens. Even though Neanderthals and Sapiens share genes responsible for development of language processing zones in the brain, Harari argues that Sapiens had a much better command and flexibility on language than Neanderthals. A glance at the skulls of the two species shows that there is a significant difference in the size of the prefrontal cortex.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/posts/blog/unsorted/sapiensNeanderthalsSkullsNHM-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/posts/blog/unsorted/sapiensNeanderthalsSkullsNHM-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/posts/blog/unsorted/sapiensNeanderthalsSkullsNHM-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/posts/blog/unsorted/sapiensNeanderthalsSkullsNHM.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="img" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> Neanderthals' skull (left) and Sapiens' skull (right) </div> <p>It seems like the size of eyes, nose and jaws of modern Sapiens has been compensated to accomodate a supposedly more important prefrontal cortex. The Sapiens’ skull in itself seems to be transformed into a more spherical shape (compared to an elongated Neanderthal skull), and spheres are mathematically proved to be able to pack the most volume with the least surface area.<br/> Of course, a bigger brain doesn’t necessarily imply more complex functioning. It’s no big news, blue whales suck at calculus.<br/> But Neanderthals could make stone tools and set traps. There has been evidence of Neanderthals conducting funeral rituals, worshipping spirit animals, and dancing to the stars as a form of recreation. The caveman was much more ingenious than what the archetypical portrayal is. So where’s the difference?<br/></p> <p>An <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4107958/">article</a> resulting from studies on neurodegenerative diseases of the pre-frontal cortex (PFC) highlights that such diseases are generally an impairment to creative tasks, albeit facilitate artistic tasks. Patients although could not succeed at general creative cognitive tasks, they performed drawings nonetheless. An inference drawn in this study is:</p> <blockquote> <p><em>Damage to the PFC may alter the intentional appropriateness and originality of patient productions by altering planning, fluency, mental flexibility, rule-based thinking, or abstraction. However, clinical observations of frontal damage patients suggest that some symptoms associated with frontal damage provoke cognitive, conative, and behavioral changes, including social disinhibition, compulsive behaviors, emotional distortions, and the relaxing of cognitive constraints, which can motivate and favor artistic productions.</em></p> </blockquote> <p><a href="https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2013/03/130314144356.htm">Another research</a> found that suppressing the conginitive filter of the brain helped in <strong>‘creative-ambling’</strong> of the brain.<br/> Conclusions from these studies point towards a subtle difference between Sapiens and Neanderthals. Even though creativity and fiction might have been a common trait, the testing of that creativity with the help of a more advanced PFC might have helped Sapiens become inventive instead of arduous, developing a logical inquisitive nature instead of a mere curious fascination.<br/> With a more advanced PFC, Sapiens may have achieved <strong>appropriate intention for hypothesizing fiction</strong>, followed by patching it up with logical rules to validate its real-life behaviour.</p> <p>Although little conclusive research has been done on the reasons of difference between the brains of the Neanderthals and Sapiens, it has been systematically hypothesized that modern cognition and the ability to manipulate and create fictitious concepts with our language has been an essential contributor.<br/> Think about it…<br/> You have been able to understand my thoughts in this article through this medium of the English language. You are essentially able to <em>reprogram</em> your brain just by reading things that I have written. The only base requisite here was knowledge of the same set of sounds, semantics, metaphors, syntax, and grammar - bundled in a neat word - <em>language</em>.</p> <hr/> <p><br/> <br/></p> <h2 id="computer-architecture">Computer Architecture</h2> <p>has developed manifold over the years. From analog computers that could perform integration in hardware directly, to finite state machines, to explicit application specific hardware, to processors being able to perform integration using a programming language - this timeline looks unnervingly similar to how evolution has been observed in the animal kingdom.<br/> From a dragonfly which is hardwired to kill in order to survive to supremely flexible humans who can contemplate suicide, natural selection has sincerely favoured dynamic adaptivity and improvisation techniques, and humans win because their brains allow them to adapt and behave differently with just the power of active fiction.<br/></p> <p>As software progresses, a limit will soon be observed on the speed of the soft and flexible processor. In an effort to be more adaptive, more skilled and more resourceful, this software will need some hardware accelerators to perform menial/repititive tasks effortlessly without the use of conscious thought. Maybe driving a car, or cutting vegetables, or lifting heavy loads, or remembering important dates in history, there are a plethora of use-cases where our fictitious brain can be supplemented.<br/> Context switches may happen only when there’s conscious thought involved - possibility of an accident, whether to slice/chop/dice, whether to store some data permanently or as a buffer, etc.<br/> I see it as nothing but deterministic to assert that it is in human’s future to be able to control some hard-wired part of their self while being involved in other complex thought.<br/> The brain is, afterall, still a black box…</p> <hr/>]]></content><author><name>Akhil Raj Baranwal</name></author><category term="blogpost"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In a world full of crazy experiments fueled by the desire to understand how we work, can we ever hack our own selves?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Yin and Yang</title><link href="https://thecurryspice.github.io/blog/2020/yin-and-yang/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Yin and Yang"/><published>2020-02-07T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-02-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://thecurryspice.github.io/blog/2020/yin-and-yang</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thecurryspice.github.io/blog/2020/yin-and-yang/"><![CDATA[<p>It has been almost a month since I came to Germany as a guest researcher at the <a href="https://cfaed.tu-dresden.de/pd-about">Chair for Processor Design, CFAED</a> for my undergraduate thesis. Dresden is a beautiful, beautiful city.<br/> For starters, here is what I get to look at each morning.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/posts/blog/unsorted/windowViewDresden-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/posts/blog/unsorted/windowViewDresden-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/posts/blog/unsorted/windowViewDresden-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/posts/blog/unsorted/windowViewDresden.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="dresdenWindowView" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> Simply elegant. </div> <hr/> <p><br/> <br/></p> <h1 id="impressions">Impressions</h1> <p>One word to sum up my impression of Germany is <strong>order</strong>. An order which forces me to strictly discipline myself according to rules/regulations/paperwork/manners/whatnot. Like a silent teacher looking down at you with a disappointed gaze, this order makes me highly aware of myself, of my actions, of my own existence as an individual in an ordered society.</p> <p>In contrast, India is pure <strong>chaos</strong>. Sheer, blissful, chaos that envelopes my identity with hers. India is like a gushing stream of freshwater. You’ll start complaining the moment you get in, and you’ll miss the fun and freedom the moment you get out.</p> <p>India and Germany are like the duality of Yin and Yang, the chaos and the order. Fun fact, Germany is referred to as Fatherland (<em>“Vaterland”</em> in Duetsch), while India is explicitly referred to as Motherland (<em>“bhaarat maata ki jai”</em> in Hindi (long live Mother India)), which fantastically support my metaphor of Yin (feminine) and Yang (masculine), of chaos and order. My stay here in Germany has helped me realise some things about myself that I didn’t know were crucial to inculcate in my daily routine. Highlighting those things/thoughts may be unintelligible because I believe it is a subjective experience, just like <em>Hajj</em> is a wholesome experience to people who visit the Mecca as a symbol of reverence.</p> <p>Sure, I miss dear home, but Germany isn’t a wildly different construct than India.<br/> Once in Germany, you can find yourself seeking chaos in the order, which is what people do on weekends here, they hang out with friends, drink, stay home, go on a weekend trip, etc.<br/> Once in India, you can find yourself seeking order in the chaos, which is what people do on weekends there, they hang out with friends, drink, stay home, go on a weekend trip, etc.</p> <hr/> <p><br/> <br/></p> <h2 id="learning-to-take-a-break">Learning to take a break</h2> <p>It’s almost funny how humans just want to take a break, be it the chaos, be it the order, but trying to excel in our domains, we become so engrossed that we forget how to simply exist peacefully. The human brain can flit 12 times a second, undoubtedly the number one champion in the animal kingdom if flitting was a competition. A masterful feat indeed.<br/> But that diverts our energies into many areas rather than on one specific activity as desired, doesn’t it?<br/> Good point, and as a workaround, we try to meditate and channel our concentration to one thing so that we can achieve superhuman capabilities in one task. Well, if we channel every bit of energy into one activity, we fail to flit 12 times a second, which in my understanding is sub-human instead of superhuman.<br/> <em>Meditation and superhuman skills thus invent a false dichotomy</em>. They represent two poles of sustainable balance with motionless thriving on one side and chaotic work output on the other.<br/> Neither focus on being superhuman, nor focus on meditation. Just learn to take a break…</p> <hr/>]]></content><author><name>Akhil Raj Baranwal</name></author><category term="blogpost"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[It has been almost a month since I came to Germany as a guest researcher at the Chair for Processor Design, CFAED for my undergraduate thesis. Dresden is a beautiful, beautiful city. For starters, here is what I get to look at each morning.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">An Epiphany on Anger</title><link href="https://thecurryspice.github.io/blog/2019/anger/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="An Epiphany on Anger"/><published>2019-05-29T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-05-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://thecurryspice.github.io/blog/2019/anger</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thecurryspice.github.io/blog/2019/anger/"><![CDATA[<p>I find myself particularly intrigued by two events:</p> <ol> <li>Thoughts that influence my actions.</li> <li>Actions that influence my thoughts.</li> </ol> <p>These things make me back off for a moment and take in the entire scenario with a much more wholesome perspective. These things make me pause, like Bangalore’s traffic.</p> <p>The last 10 days in Bangalore have been particularly profound because of this reason.<br/> For reasons that we’ll consider not really important for now, I travel for more than 35 kilometres a day, spanning a total of 3 hours.</p> <p>The insane traffic in Bangalore teaches anger-management, if not patience.<br/> There are people who are vexed by the traffic, their souls absolutely miserable and hollow from inside.<br/> Meeting people in such traffic is mostly like meeting a small kid who’s really annoyed. Any direct interaction with the kid will lead to a more annoyed state. (Ice-creams might help, though. Ice-creams always help).<br/> Yet, there are others who are much more patient to external stimuli. They seem calm and composed, which leads me to think why people get angry.</p> <h2 id="an-annoyed-kid">An Annoyed Kid</h2> <p>Think of an annoyed little boy.<br/> Maybe he is annoyed because he didn’t get to play a game, or maybe he didn’t get what he was promised for lunch, or maybe he doesn’t like the boring family function he has been forced to attend.<br/> <strong>But why is the kid annoyed?</strong><br/> There must definitely be something that is troubling him, because kids usually have tons of hope and enthusiasm and easily find something to engage with.<br/> An annoyed kid, therefore, doesn’t have much to engage with and doesn’t accept this reality being forced on him. He hopes for a different reality; a reality where he got to play the game, where he got what he was promised for lunch, and where he wasn’t dragged to a boring family function.</p> <p>The crux of this is the understanding that it is because this kid is being such a wild optimist that he gets annoyed with his present situation.</p> <p>The questions:<br/> “Why didn’t I get to play this game?”<br/> “Why didn’t I get the lunch I was promised?”<br/> “Why do I have to go to the family function?”</p> <p>are actually based in:<br/> “How can I get to play this game?”<br/> “How can I get the lunch I was promised?”<br/> “How can I evade the family function?”</p> <p>Most angry and annoyed people, just beneath their external demeanour, conceal an innocent and optimistic kid, who’s constantly hoping for an alternate reality.<br/> To me, this realisation, that <strong>optimism drives most of people’s anger</strong>, is inexplicably profound.<br/> These thoughts intrigue me because they completely change the normal standard of responses towards an angry individual.<br/> It helps me look at angry people with pity instead of derision and concern instead of fear. I can only be sorry for a kid, never deride him.<br/> And I can never be afraid of an optimistic kid, I’ll rather be concerned that he gets what he wants.</p> <hr/> <p>Wait, does that mean people at peace have accepted the pessimism this world is built upon?</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="blogpost"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I find myself particularly intrigued by two events: Thoughts that influence my actions. Actions that influence my thoughts.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Tea And Compliments</title><link href="https://thecurryspice.github.io/blog/2019/tea-and-compliments/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Tea And Compliments"/><published>2019-05-17T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-05-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://thecurryspice.github.io/blog/2019/tea-and-compliments</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thecurryspice.github.io/blog/2019/tea-and-compliments/"><![CDATA[<p>I love tea. Freshly poured out, steaming, I compare its vapours to the fragrance of incense sticks. Both are equally adept at refreshing a dull room, and my mood.<br/> However much of an elixir it looks like, tea is always meant to be sipped.</p> <p>I take in compliments like I take in tea.<br/> I sip on tea.<br/> I know that I’ll burn my tongue if I take it in all at once.<br/> It will make my tongue immune to any other thing I taste, be it tea or coffee. My taste-buds will stop functioning and for some time, I wouldn’t respond to different flavours that I taste.<br/> Thanks to tea, I don’t outright reject any beverage that is offered to me, but I sip it slowly. People seem to like it that way.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="blogpost"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I love tea. Freshly poured out, steaming, I compare its vapours to the fragrance of incense sticks. Both are equally adept at refreshing a dull room, and my mood. However much of an elixir it looks like, tea is always meant to be sipped.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Why Good People Are… Good</title><link href="https://thecurryspice.github.io/blog/2018/why-good-people-are-good/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why Good People Are… Good"/><published>2018-12-20T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2018-12-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://thecurryspice.github.io/blog/2018/why-good-people-are-good</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thecurryspice.github.io/blog/2018/why-good-people-are-good/"><![CDATA[<p>I love travelling, it teaches me a lot. There are incidents that push me to think and ponder.<br/> I came across one such incident recently while travelling in a train. I was carrying some pretty heavy luggage, but I was determined <a href="https://melmagazine.com/en-us/story/why-men-feel-like-they-have-to-carry-all-their-groceries-inside-in-one-trip">to carry all of it in one trip</a>.<br/></p> <p>After boarding the train and hauling everything clumsily with all the luggage sloppying around me, I reached my compartment and found one guy sitting peacefully on the lower berth. Since my boarding-point and my destination, both, were terminals for the train’s route, I wanted to push my luggage deep into the abyssmal depth under the lower berth he was sitting on. Although he looked like a perfectly well-educated man, he probably couldn’t comprehend my gesture of drawing his legs up. So I politely asked him,<br/> “Would you mind helping me?”<br/> and out came the most disturbing answer I had ever had to listen to,<br/> “Why?”<br/> That man asked me <strong>why</strong> he should help me! Although his question had made perfect sense, and I would have developed deep respect for him had he given me a smirk a second later and pulled his legs up, he was brutal enough to look me in the eye and demand an answer!<br/> As I pushed my luggage beneath the opposite berth, his <em>why</em> got me thinking about the reasons people would be willing to help and also the reasons people would expect to be helped.</p> <h2 id="a-fair-game">A Fair Game</h2> <p>What is your idea of a fair game?<br/> Take a moment and think.<br/> It may be a game where every player wins.<br/> Or it might be a game in which some win and some lose. Or a game in which some win and some lose <em>with equal probability</em>.<br/> Yes, this is important - probabilities of winning and losing being equal. Why though? Because it is only when the probabilities of winning and losing are equal that people in general are willing to play the game, <em>again and again</em>.<br/> What else can be important? Rules, definitely. All-binding rules with no exceptions and corner cases seem legitimate. Why? Because it is an assertion of the equal probability.</p> <p>Now that we have defined our ‘fair’ game, we realise that it is actually a game where there is only <strong>one</strong> final output for a player (either in favour or against, determining his win or loss). Examples can include a simple coin-toss, or rolling a dice after clearly indicating what 3 numbers will result in a win.</p> <p>Let us consider a fair game with 2 people playing in all honesty. Considering that the game indeed, is fair, two conditions must hold:</p> <ol> <li>Probabilities of winning and losing are equal.</li> <li>None of the players enjoy any kind of priveleges like second-chances, quota, seat-reservations, and the like.</li> </ol> <p><strong>For a fair game, it should be obvious that if one wins, the other loses.</strong></p> <h2 id="but-life-isnt-fair">But Life Isn’t Fair</h2> <p>“But hey!”, you ask.<br/> Sure, no sane person in his right mind should expect life to be fair, except for some fortunate events of heightened romanticism for faith in the spirit-of-the-universe that makes us believe in some hallucinating and misleading concepts like <em>karma</em>, which is used for nothing but to console people so that they refrain from taking malicious revenge.</p> <p>Let’s not deviate and try to define an unfair game instead.<br/> Deriving from the fair game, the unfair game</p> <ol> <li>might have a clear bias in the winning or losing chances, i.e, the probability of winning will clearly be either towards 1 (a safe game) or towards 0 (a risky game).</li> <li>might have slightly different rules in a way which makes one person have higher chances of winning (a truly unfair game).</li> </ol> <p>Be it through the instructions given as a child, or through the learnings and experiences of the adult nature, people tend to boil <em>transactions</em> in daily life to one of the games mentioned above (fair, unfair, risky, safe). By transaction, I mean any event that acts as enough of a stimulus to elicit a reaction that forces two people to acknowledge each others’ presence in a given setting.<br/> In my understanding, people’s decisions in life are influenced largely by the kind of game they <em>perceive</em> the transaction as. They then participate by determining their chances of winning or losing and take decisions in their best interest.<br/> It is, therefore, nothing but obvious that in a neutral transaction involving strangers, a dull brain is bound to perceive it as a fair game. A dull brain is bound to believe that one’s win necessitates the other’s loss.<br/> A dull brain sees the obvious win for the other person, but weighs in heavily on the idea of a fair game!<br/> In essence, a dull brain is bound to assume that helping someone <del>might</del> will result in its loss.</p> <h2 id="why-are-good-people-good">Why Are Good People Good?</h2> <p>Because a bright brain understands the failure in the games described above - <strong>the missing idea of a <em>non-zero sum game</em></strong>. It understands that games can be fun for both players and that games are not just about wins or losses. It understands that transactions can be investments, and are not as shallow as a simple coin toss. It knows that the universe is not putting all its energies conspiring against one specific person. It understands that it is not the only bright brain in all humanity.<br/> But most importantly, it believes, that for it to win, it doesn’t need to necessitate someone’s loss.<br/> This is why they are good, because they don’t intend harm to succeed, to win. The brilliant thing is, they might even intend someone else’s benefit for their win, all because of their belief in a non-zero sum game!</p> <p>Moral of this discourse? At times when you see that you clearly can’t win, start focusing on someone else’s win, you might be playing a non-zero sum game ;)</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="blogpost"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I love travelling, it teaches me a lot. There are incidents that push me to think and ponder. I came across one such incident recently while travelling in a train. I was carrying some pretty heavy luggage, but I was determined to carry all of it in one trip.]]></summary></entry></feed>